Register of the Vernon Lyman Kellogg papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vernon Lyman Kellogg papers
1902-1932
56004
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder (4.7 linear feet)
Writings, printed matter, photographs, drawings, and certificates relating to relief work in Belgium during World War I, the relief activities of Herbert Hoover, and the world food problem.
Kellogg, Vernon L. (Vernon Lyman), 1867-1937.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1956.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Charlotte Hoffman Kellogg papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Commission for Relief in Belgium records, Hoover Institution Archives
United States Food Administration records, Hoover Institution Archives
Jean Kellogg Dickie collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Kellogg-Dickie papers, Yale University Library Manuscripts and Archives
Separated Materials
Materials related to Charlotte Kellogg have been moved to the Charlotte Hoffman Kellogg papers.
Biographical Note
1867 December 1 Born, Emporia, Kansas
1889 Bachelor of Science, University of Kansas
1890-1893 Assistant professor of entomology, University of Kansas
1892 Master of Science, University of Kansas
1893-1894 Associate professor of entomology, University of Kansas
1894-1895 Assistant and associate professor of entomology, Stanford University
1896-1920 Professor of entomology, and of entomology and bionomics, Stanford University
1908 Married Charlotte Hoffman
1910 Daughter, Jean Kellogg, born in Berkeley, California
1915-1916 Director, Brussels, American Commission for Relief in Belgium
1917-1919 Assistant to U.S. food administrator; Chief of mission to Poland, American Relief Administration
1918 Chairman, Division of Agriculture, National Research Council
1918-1921 Special investigator in Russia, American Relief Administration
1919-1934 Various positions for the National Research Council, including permanent secretary
1920-1931 Director and member, Executive Committee of Commission for Relief in Belgium Educational Foundation
1921-1933 Member, board of trustees, Science Service
1922-1932 Member, Executive Committee of the Rockefeller Foundation
1925-1931 Member, Executive Committee of International Research Council
1931 Secretary emeritus, National Research Council
1937 August 8 Died, Hartford, Connecticut
Scope and Content of Collection
The Vernon Lyman Kellogg papers include writings, correspondence, printed matter, photographs, and certificates relating to relief work in Belgium and Poland during World War I, the relief activities of Herbert Hoover, and the world food problem.
In addition to his scientific work, Vernon Kellogg was involved in various relief efforts, including the Commission for Relief in Belgium as the director in Brussels, where he was later joined by his wife Charlotte Hoffman Kellogg. The Biographical File contains a biographical sketch listing positions he held throughout his career, as well as a bibliography of his numerous published works. Some of those works can be found in the Speeches and Writings series, which contains writings by Kellogg concerning relief efforts, Herbert Hoover, and the world food problem.
The Relief Work File relates to Kellogg's involvement in the Commission for Relief in Belgium and the United States Food Administration, including Kellogg's travel documentation. The correspondence includes a letter from Herbert Hoover.
The Oversize Material includes materials related to Kellogg's relief work, such as a photo album with pictures of members of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, as well as various awards that Kellogg received for his aid efforts. In addition, the file includes Kellogg's diplomas, a children's book written in French, and a tracing of a Colorado River map used on a trip that took place from December 1901 to January 1902.
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Commission for Relief in Belgium (1914-1930); American Relief Administration.; United States Food Administration.; Food supply.; International relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Belgium.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Food supply.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.; Drawing.
- Biographical File, 1916, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes a biographical sketch, clippings, and photographs. Arranged alphabetically by format.
  - Biographical sketch, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Envelope from the White House, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Includes handwritten list of diplomas.
  - Photographs of Vernon Kellogg, undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Speeches and Writings, 1916-1921
  Includes manuscripts, typescripts, reprints, and clippings related to relief work, Herbert Hoover, and the world food problem. Arranged chronologically.
  - Review of The Children of Warsaw, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - "La France et la Belgique occupées," reprint, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Articles by Vernon Kellogg, clippings, 1916-1921 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - The Food Problem by Vernon Kellogg and Alonzo Taylor, typescript, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Mes Soirées au Grand Quartier, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    Preface by Theodore Roosevelt.
  - Herbert Hoover and His Work, manuscript and typescript, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 10-11)
- Relief Work File, 1914-1919
  Includes correspondence, awards, printed matter, and travel documentation. Arranged alphabetically by format. See also: Oversize Material.
  - Awards, rubbing of medal awarded to Vernon Kellogg by the Government of Poland, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Clippings on students and World War I, 1914-1919 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Correspondence
    - Carton de Wiart, Adrian, circa 1916 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Jusserand, Jean Jules, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Thierry, Adrien, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - White, John Beaver, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Passports, ID cards, letters of certification, and other travel documents, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Travel documents of Charlotte Kellogg have been separated to her collection.
  - Printed matter, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - United States Food Administration license regulations, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1916-1918, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Oversize Material, circa 1902-1932
  Includes awards, diplomas, portrait drawings, and a photo album related to relief work, as well as a children's book dedicated to Kellogg's daughter and a map of the Colorado River containing Kellogg's notes. Includes original housing for posters.
  - Awards, 1918-1930 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    Includes National Order of the Legion of Honor; United States Food Administration certificate; Council of the American Geographical Society certificate for election as a fellow; and National Academy of Sciences certificate of membership.
  - Diplomas, 1919-1932 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Les aventures merveilleuses du petit Floridor et de son chien Carabi by Ernest Picard, undated (Box-folder 3: 3)
    Dedicated to Jean Kellogg from three Belgian children and others. Includes photograph of three children.
  - Passport, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Popular Science award committee posters, undated (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Portraits by H. Lemaire, undated (Box 4)
    Drawings with signatures. Includes portraits of Herbert Hoover and Vernon Kellogg.
  - Photo album, undated (Box 5)
    Members of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, 78 prints.
  - Médaille Commémorative du Comité National, Belgium certificate, 1919 (Map case)
  - Tracing of Map of Colorado River from Needles to Yuma from [Ives] Expedition (1857-1858), circa 1902 (Map case)
    Includes notes of Vernon Kellogg during a trip from December 21, 1901, to January 3, 1902.